Finding Aid for Douglas Ross Papers, 1967-2002
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Douglas Ross Papers 1967-2002
Ross, Douglas, 1942-
8 linear feet
861071 Aa 2
Douglas Ross (1942- ) is a Michigan political figure. He has been active in many political organizations and the Democratic party and served as Michigan Director of Commerce and United States Assistant Secretary of Labor. He also ran, unsuccessfully, for governor of Michigan in 1998. Ross’ main concerns are economic policy and education. He currently runs a charter school in Detroit, Michigan. The papers cover most of his career, especially as Michigan Senator and at the Department of Labor, and include his notes and articles, correspondence, publications, and videotapes.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection is the gift of Douglas Ross (donor no. 7164 ) and came to the library in two principal accessions, 1985 and 2005.
The collection is open to research.
Douglas Ross was born on June 15, 1942. He attended Mumford High School in Detroit, graduating in 1960. He received a B.A. in history from the University of Michigan (1965), pursued graduate studies in economics at the University of Michigan (1965-1966), and the London School of Economics (1964), and received a master's degree in public affairs from Princeton University (1972).
He has held numerous positions in government, public interest, and business, working for various politicians and political activist groups. In 1967, Ross created and co-directed the Volunteer Placement Corps, an organization funded by New Detroit, Inc., to place inner-city high school graduates in colleges, job training programs, and jobs. In 1973, along with University of Michigan classmate Barbara Grossman, Ross founded the Michigan Citizens Lobby, a non-profit citizens group which has grown to over 100,000 members. Under his leadership, the Lobby was the moving force in the passage of the Generic Prescription Act, the Auto Repair Protection Act, and the repeal of the sales tax on food and medicine. He also served briefly as executive director of Michigan Common Cause in 1975.
In 1978, Ross left the Michigan Citizens Lobby to run for the State Senate from his home district in Oak Park. He was successful and remained in the State Senate until his unsuccessful bid for a seat in U.S. Congress in 1982.
Ross continued his political career by serving as Director of Commerce from 1984-1989 under Governor Blanchard, where he was instrumental in reshaping Michigan's economic strategy, worked to make Michigan more attractive to corporations for investment, and re-organized the department to function like a business. He left to serve as president of the Corporation for Enterprise Development, an economic-growth consulting firm.
Ross founded Michigan Future in 1991 and served as the president. It is a bipartisan group of business and community leaders working to instigate a change and revitalization in Michigan's economy. Through his economic work, Ross became involved with president-elect Bill Clinton. Ross was appointed Assistant Secretary for Employment and Training Administration (ETA) in the U.S. Department of Labor in 1993. During his tenure, the ETA underwent a structural re-organization and focused on improving worker training programs to lower unemployment. He left the post in 1995.
Doug Ross had begun working as a visiting lecturer at the University of Michigan in 1991. He resumed his teaching when he returned from Washington in 1995. He ran for Michigan Governor in 1998, but lost in the Democratic Primaries to Geoffrey Fieger. Ross then focused his energy on founding a charter school in Detroit. He opened the University Preparatory Academy in 2000 to provide better education for urban youth. The school consists of a middle school and a high school and provides small classes and a customized education. Ross continues to serve as principal of the school.
The Douglas Ross papers are divided into thirteen series. Each series records Ross' involvement with an organization or government agency. The series are largely arranged chronologically. Excepted are the Personal, Schedule and Videotapes series which contain materials from various periods in Ross' career.
Subjects:
Charter schools--Michigan.; Consumer protection--Michigan.; Corporation for Enterprise Development.; Democratic Party (Mich.); Elections--Michigan--1972.; Elections--Michigan--1982.; Elections--Michigan--1998.; Immigrants--Michigan.; Michigan--Emigration and immigration.; Michigan. Legislature. Senate.; Michigan--Politics and government--1971-1980.; Michigan--Politics and government--1981-1990.; Michigan--Politics and government--1991-2000.; Michigan--Politics and government--1951-; Recall--Michigan.; Social action--Michigan--Societies, etc.; Taxation--Michigan.; Tisch, Robert.; United States. Employment and Training Administration.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Chavez, Cesar, 1927-1993; Kennedy, Edward M. (Edward Moore), 1932-2009; Milliken, William G., 1922-; Ross, Douglas, 1942-
Subjects - Sound Recordings:
Ross, Douglas, 1942-; Tax and expenditure limitations--Michigan.
Contributors: Sound Recordings:
Tisch, Robert.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.; Sound recordings.; Videotapes.
- Personal
  Personal (0.5 linear feet, 1968-1993) includes materials about Ross from throughout his career, documented with newspaper articles and photographs. The majority of the series is composed of notes and articles Ross wrote on a variety of subjects, including education, politics and economics.
  - Correspondence 1972-1975 (Box 1)
  - Michiganians of the Year Award 1989 (Box 1)
  - Newspaper Clippings 1986-1993 (Box 1)
  - Photographs (Box 1)
    (includes formal and informal portraits, swearing in ceremony, bill-signing ceremony with Governor William Milliken, and speaking engagements)
  - Writings
    - "Congressmen and pollution: the gentlemen's agreement," with Harold Wolman 1970 (Box 1)
    - Federal Aid to Education Series 1971 (Box 1)
      (three papers on the Elementary and Secondary Education Act)
    - Industrial Democracy, untitled analysis undated (Box 1)
    - "Looking Forward to 1972," 1971 (for ZPG National Reporter) (Box 1)
    - "Making Politicians into Demographers and vice versa," undated (Box 1)
    - New Politics, articles and speeches 1988-1990 (Box 1)
    - Robert F. Kennedy: Apostle of Change, 1968 (Box 1)
      (includes introduction to the book, press release, and royalty statements)
    - Speech Notes undated (Box 1)
    - Student Notes, ca. 1971-1972 (Box 1)
    - Student Papers 1970-1977 (Box 1)
    - "War, Politics and the 1968 Election," circa 1968 (Box 1)
    - "What's Working in Michigan?" book deal 1993 (Box 1)
    - WXYZ-TV Scripts for Economics Program undated (Box 1)
- Schedule
  Schedule (1.0 linear feet, 1968-2002) provides a record of Ross' meetings and activities throughout his career. The series is composed of appointment books and task lists. The years 1968 to 1985 are covered through appointment books, listing who he was meeting and the topic of discussion but with little detail. The task lists cover 1999-2002. They are lists of meetings, tasks, and goals to be accomplished for that day, week, or month. They have a little more detail than the appointment books. Most entries pertain to Ross founding and running the University Preparatory Academy, a charter school, but also include tasks related to teaching at the University of Michigan and paying off his debt from the gubernatorial race.
  - 1968, 1973-1975, 4 volumes (Box 1)
  - 1978-1982, 12 volumes (Box 1)
  - 1999, 4 folders (Box 2)
  - 2000, 4 folders (Box 2)
  - 2001-February 2002, 4 folders (Box 2)
  - March-October 2002, 3 folders (Box 2)
- Political Involvement 1960s, 1970s
  Political Involvement 1960's and 1970's (0.5 linear feet, 1967-1972) contains materials related to Ross' early involvement in politics. It includes papers related to his work for various politicians and political groups. He founded the Michigan Citizens Lobby, which worked to get laws passed to benefit citizens, and served as executive director of Common Cause.
  - Volunteer Placement Corps 1967-1968 (Box 2)
  - Legislative Aide to Senator Joseph Tydings (D-MD) 1969-1970, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Speechwriter for U.N. Ambassador Sol Linowitz (Box 2)
  - Kelley campaign 1972 (Box 2)
  - Michigan Citizens Lobby (Box 2)
  - Common Cause (Box 2)
- Michigan State Senate
  Michigan State Senate (1 linear foot, 1977-1982) documents Doug Ross' term in the Michigan State Senate. There are substantive files on a recall campaign against him, the Independent Business Research Institute in Michigan, the Democratic Citizens Caucus, Royal Oak Township services, and two Russian families whose emigration Ross assisted. There are also campaign financial records, news releases, newsletters, bills, clippings, and constituent mail.
  - Biographical (Box 2)
  - Advisory committees (Box 2)
  - Bills introduced by Ross 1979-1981, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Book 1979-1980 (Box 2)
    (proposed book by Ross and Morley Winograd on a strategy for reviving the Democratic party)
  - Clippings-News Articles (Box 3)
  - Correspondence 1981-1982 (Box 3)
  - Democratic Citizens Caucus 1979-1981 (Box 3)
    (Ross co-chair with Representative Debbie Stabenow)
  - Expenses 1979-1981, 3 folders (Box 3)
  - Financial Disclosure 1977-1979 (Box 3)
  - Independent Business Research Institute in Michigan 1980-1982 (Box 3)
    (Ross served on board of directors)
  - Individual Contributor Records 1978 (Box 3)
  - Lobbyists: 1982 list of registered legislative agents (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 3)
  - News releases 1979-1982, 3 folders (Box 3)
  - Newsletters 1979-1981 (Box 3)
  - Personal 1979-1982 (Box 3)
  - Recall File 1981 (Box 3)
  - Rifkin family 1979 (Box 3)
    (Ross' efforts on behalf of Russian family seeking to emigrate)
  - "The Ross Report," 1980-1982 (Box 3)
    (scripts and notes from weekly public affairs interview show for WCAR radio)
  - Ross-Tisch Debate on Proposal D 1980, two audio cassettes (Box 3)
  - Royal Oak Township 1982 (Box 3)
    (fire and police protection)
  - Speeches/Articles by Douglas Ross undated (Box 3)
  - Stolar family 1982 (Box 3)
- United States Congress Campaign
  United States Congress Campaign (0.2 linear feet, 1977-1982) includes papers related to Ross' unsuccessful campaign for United States Congress in 1982. The series is composed of newspaper articles, correspondence, and campaign advertisement materials.
  - Clippings 1977-1982, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Correspondence 1982 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence after Losing Race 1982 (Box 3)
  - Financing the Campaign 1982 (Box 3)
  - Publicity Materials 1982 (Box 3)
  - Publicity Materials, "Contract with Constituents," 1982 (Box 3)
- Michigan Department of Commerce
  Michigan Department of Commerce (0.2 linear feet, 1983-1993) documents Ross' service as Director of Commerce under the Blanchard Administration from 1984 to 1989. He worked to change Michigan's image to make the state more attractive for investment by corporations at a time when Michigan's economy was struggling and reorganized the Commerce Department. The papers include documents on economic strategy for Michigan and newspaper articles and correspondence as people react to his resignation.
  - Articles 1989-1993 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence 1975-1989 (Box 4)
    (majority are regarding his resignation)
  - Economic Development, notes and research 1983-1984 (Box 4)
  - Michigan Economic Strategy, article and speech by Ross undated (Box 4)
  - "The Michigan Strategy: Building the Future," report to Legislature 1988-1989 (Box 4)
  - "The Path to Prosperity," findings of the Task Force for a Long Term Economic Strategy for Michigan 1984 (Box 4)
  - Photographs (Box 4)
  - Resignation 1989, 2 folders (Box 4)
- Corporation for Enterprise Development (CFED)
  Corporation for Enterprise Development (CFED) (0.2 linear feet, 1989-1999) contains papers from when Ross was president of the corporation, an economic consulting group located in Washington, D.C. The papers include publications by the group, information on the staff, and articles on the theory of "Third Wave Economics."
  - "Ideas in Development" Conference 1999 (Box 4)
  - Memoranda 1989-1992, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Publications 1990-1998, undated, 3 folders (Box 4)
  - Staff Directory 1999 (Box 4)
  - Third Wave Economics 1990 (Box 4)
- Political Involvement 1990s
  Political Involvement 1990's (0.2 linear feet, 1992-1998) includes papers from Ross' involvement with three political organizations: the Democratic Leadership Council (DLC), Michigan Future, and the Progressive Foundation. Ross founded Michigan Future in 1991 and served as the president. It is a bipartisan group of business and community leaders, working to instigate a change and revitalization in Michigan's economy.
  - Democrat Leadership Council (DLC)
    - Memos to Bill Clinton 1992-1993, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Publications 1992 (Box 4)
  - Michigan Future
    - Bill Clinton 1992 (Box 4)
    - Bill Clinton, Economic Summit and Offering Ross a Position 1992 (Box 4)
    - Reports 1992-1998 (Box 4)
    - Shelter Development Corp. (SCA) Consulting Project 1991 (Box 4)
  - Progressive Foundation 1993-1995 (Box 4)
- University of Michigan (UM) School of Public Policy
  The University of Michigan (UM) School of Public Policy series (0.25 linear feet, 1991-2000) is comprised of papers relating to several classes Ross taught as a lecturer at the University of Michigan School of Public Policy, starting in 1991. The papers include syllabi, class notes, and student evaluations. Ross taught undergraduate and graduate seminars on government, economic development, and education reform.
  - Appointment as Lecturer 1991, 1995 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence regarding building a reading list 1995-1999 (Box 4)
  - Freshman Undergraduate Seminar, Why Government Doesn't Work Anymore and What You Can Do About It (Box 4)
  - SPP 691, Education Reform: Designing Schools that Work (Box 4)
  - SPP 694, Economic Development at the State, Local, and Community Level, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - SPP 698, Practical Politics: Making a Difference in the Public Arena (Box 4)
  - Student Evaluations of the Classes 1995-2000, 2 folders (Box 5)
- U.S. Department of Labor, Employment and Training Administration (DOL-ETA)
  The U.S. Department of Labor, Employment and Training Administration (DOL-ETA) series (2 linear feet, 1993-1995) includes materials from Ross' position as the Assistant Secretary for Employment and Training Administration during the Clinton Administration. The papers document his activities as well as those of the ETA. During his tenure, the ETA underwent a structural re-organization. They also worked on the Workforce Security Act of 1994 and focused on creating better programs for training workers to lower unemployment. His personal involvement in the organization is best documented in the "Ross, Douglas" subseries, and includes speeches, articles about him, and papers related to welcoming him and bidding him farewell from the department.
  - ETA Discretionary Funds 1993 (Box 5)
  - ETA Organizational Structure
    - ETA Reinvention 1993-1994, 3 folders (Box 5)
    - Organizational Charts 1994-1994 (Box 5)
    - Organizational Development 1993 (Box 5)
    - Streamlining Plan 1994 (Box 5)
  - Labor Programs 1993-1994, 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Memos from Robert Reich, Labor Secretary 1993-1994 (Box 5)
  - Memos from Douglas Ross 1993-1994 (Box 5)
  - NAFTA 1993-1994 (Box 5)
  - Presidential Partners 1993 (Box 5)
  - Press Clippings 1993-1995, 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Re-employment Act 1994 (Box 5)
    (testimony to legislature)
  - Ross, Douglas
    - Appointment Book 1995 (Box 5)
    - Confirmation for Assistant Secretary-Employment and Training Post 1993, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Farewell Reception, Correspondence 1995 (Box 6)
    - Farewell Reception Photographs, 1995 (Box 6)
    - Financial Disclosure Reports 1992-1995 (Box 6)
    - "Ideas" undated (Box 6)
      (list of goals for DOL)
    - Newspaper Articles 1993-1995 (Box 6)
    - Performance Agreement between Ross and Reich 1994 (Box 6)
    - Photographs undated (Box 6)
    - Speech Files 1993-1995, 4 folders (Box 6)
    - Thank You Correspondence to Ross 1993-1995 (Box 6)
  - Strategy Reports 1994, undated (Box 6)
  - Unions 1994-1995, 2 folders (Box 6)
  - Work, Achievement, Values and Education (WAVE) Program, Discontinuing Non-Competitive Grant 1994 (Box 6)
  - Welfare 1992-1994 (Box 6)
  - Workforce Initiative Strategy and One-Stop Career Centers 1993, 2 folders (Box 6)
  - The Workforce Security Act of 1994 the Boiler Room Team at ETA, 1993, 3 folders (Box 6)
- Michigan Governor Campaign
  The Michigan Governor Campaign (0.5 linear feet, 1996-1998) documents Ross' campaign for Michigan Governor, which he lost in the Democratic Primaries in 1998 to Geoffrey Fieger. Most of the papers pertain to fundraising and publicity, as well as his campaign strategy. The 3.5 floppy disk contains a 49 page Campaign Plan, as well as several shorter documents on his campaign, which are in Microsoft Word 6.0.
  - Campaign Strategy 1997, 2 folders (Box 7)
    (includes 3.5" floppy disk)
  - Correspondence after losing the primary 1998 (Box 7)
  - Fundraising January 1997-July 1998, 3 folders (Box 7)
  - HOPE Proposal 1998 (Box 7)
  - Publicity
    - Clippings 1996-1998 (Box 7)
    - Flyers 1998 (Box 7)
    - Photographs (Box 7)
      (publicity tour and Ross with ministers)
    - Photographs (Box 7)
      (speeches and meeting people)
  - Ross Record Analysis, potential attacks and responses 1997 (Box 7)
- University Preparatory Academy
  The University Preparatory Academy series (0.5 linear feet, 1998-1999) contains the materials gathered by Ross in preparation for founding a charter school in Detroit, MI. The majority of the papers are research materials he gathered while planning the school. Also included are floor plans for the school and documents defining the purpose and organization of the school. He founded the school in 2000 to provide better education for urban youth. It consists of a middle and a high school.
  - Architectural Drawings, concepts for floor plan April 2000 (Box 7)
  - Career Prep Program undated (Box 7)
  - Education Notes undated (Box 7)
  - Leona Group 1999 (Box 7)
    (charter school management company)
  - Michigan Association of Public School Academies (MAPSA) 1999 (Box 7)
  - Research and Visiting Charter Schools 1999, 2 folders (Box 7)
  - Visiting Charter Schools: Henry Ford Academy 1998-1999 (Box 7)
- Videotapes
  Videotapes (38 tapes, 1980-1998) includes tapes from throughout Ross' career. The tapes include speeches by Ross, Ross' work for WXYZ-TV Detroit as an economic and political analyst, and news coverage on the Michigan Gubernatorial race. They document Ross as Director of Commerce, President of CFED, Assistant Secretary of Labor, and running for Michigan Governor. The tapes are arranged in chronological order.
  (VHS tapes unless otherwise noted)
  - Archive Reel WXYZ-TV Detroit 7 Action News April 11, 1983, U-matic tape (Box 7)
    (tape no. 1)
  - WXYZ-TV-7 spots undated, U-matic tape (Box 7)
    (tape no. 2)
  - Rural Economic Development Speech undated (Box 7)
    (tape no. 3)
  - 7 Steps to Success For Regional Economies Speech undated (Box 7)
    (tape no. 4)
  - Speech on education and the HOPE scholarship undated (Box 7)
    (tape no. 5)
  - Economic Analyst for WXYZ-TV Detroit 1983-1984 (Box 8)
    (tape no. 6)
  - Interviewed as Michigan Director of Commerce Newsmaker, 1984-1989 (Box 8)
    (tape no. 7)
  - Receiving NCA Award for his work as Michigan Director of Commerce 1984-1989 (Box 8)
    (tape no. 8)
  - "Michigan, State of the Future," advertisement video on why companies should move to Michigan June 10, 1987 (Box 8)
    (tape no. 9)
  - Democratic National Platform Committee, Economic Platform, Detroit June 2, 1988 (Box 8)
    (tape no. 10)
  - Impersonating Elvis Presley January 28, 1989 (Box 8)
    (tape no. 11)
  - Michigan Department of Commerce Orbital Engine Plan Announcement, Australian company invests in Michigan industry August 2, 1989 (Box 8)
    (tape no. 12)
  - "A Regional Report Card," Baltimore Regional Council of Governments, presentation as consultant from CFED 1989-1991 (Box 8)
    (tape no. 13)
  - DLC Conference Speech 1990 (Box 8)
    (tape no. 14)
  - Economic Conference December 15, 1992 (Box 8)
    (tape no. 15)
  - "Progress Report," interviewed as Assistant Secretary of Labor on innovative worker training programs 1993-1995 (Box 8)
    (tape no. 16)
  - The Enterprise "A New Idea," Department of Labor July 11, 1995 (Box 8)
    (tape no. 17)
  - Detroit Newspaper Strike, Worker Replacement, Doug Ross and Bill Johnson News Commentary WXYZ-TV Detroit News, 1996 (Box 8)
    (tape no. 18)
  - Political Corruption, Doug Ross and Bill Johnson News Commentary WXYZ-TV Detroit News, 1996 (Box 8)
    (tape no. 19)
  - Flat Tax, Doug Ross and Bill Johnson News Commentary WXYZ-TV Detroit News, July 3, 1996 and June27 1996 (Box 8)
    (tape no. 20)
  - Vice President Candidates for Bob Dole, Doug Ross and Candice Miller News Commentary WXYZ-TV Detroit, April 9, 1996 (Box 8)
    (tape no. 21)
  - Interviewed on the Clinton campaign and the Democratic Party Ideology Off The Record, August 1996 (Box 8)
    (tape no. 22)
  - Governor Campaign Kick Off Speech 1996 (Box 8)
    (video quality is poor, audio quality is fine)
    (tape no. 23)
  - Governor Campaign Kickoff News Coverage Off the Record, June 18, 1996 (Box 8)
    (tape no. 24)
  - News Coverage of Ross governor campaign Detroit TV News (Box 8)
    (tape no. 25)
  - Interviewed as a candidate for governor Law Talk, March 20, 1997 (Box 8)
    (tape no. 26)
  - Brief campaign speech on road quality, Flint Spotlight on the News, May 3, 1997 (Box 8)
    (tape no. 27)
  - Global Connections Globalizing Michigan, Doug Ross, Candidate for Governor Bloomfield Community Television, June 1997 (Box 8)
    (tape no. 28)
  - Governor Campaign Debate Tape August 1, 1997 (Box 8)
    (tape no. 29)
  - Election 1998 (Box 8)
    (tape no. 30)
  - In Kalamazoo May 5, 1998 (Box 8)
    (tape no. 31)
  - Political Candidate Doug Ross, Greater Grace Temple of the Apostolic Faith May 6, 1998 (Box 8)
    (tape no. 32)
  - MTLA: Darrell Tennis, Virgil Smith, Buzz Thomas, Kathy Bogas, Larry Owen, Geoffrey Fieger, Doug Ross Q/A Session May 15, 1998 (Box 8)
    (tape no. 33)
  - Governor Campaign, several advertisement spots June 23, 1998 (Box 8)
    (tape no. 34)
  - Interview as candidate for governor West Michigan Week, June 26, 1998 (Box 8)
    (tape no. 35)
  - Governor Primary Debate with Larry Owen July 1998 (Box 8)
    (tape no. 36)
  - Governor Campaign advertising spots, "Ideas," "Parents," "Dreams," and Appendix July 7, 1998 (Box 8)
    (tape no. 37)
  - Governor Campaign advertising spots, "Trust" and "Better," July 28, 1998 (Box 8)
    (tape no. 38)